Your eyes are extremely sensitive, so when dealing with eye injuries, our first and most
important rule is never rub an injured eye.
Rubbing can push a foreign object deeper or cause it to scratch the surface of the eye,
making the injury much worse.
As you assess the patient, ask them a few key questions.
Did anything hit your eye?
Does it feel like something is still in there?
Can you open your eye and can you still see well?
If someone has a foreign object like dust or a small piece of debris in their eye and
blinking doesn't clear it, your next step is to rinse the eye with clean water.
If you see an item stuck under an eyelid, you can gently use sterile gauze to lift the
lid and remove the visible debris.
However, if the object is embedded or you simply cannot get it out, stop what you are
doing, cover both eyes to prevent movement, and wait for EMS to arrive.
When you are dealing with chemical injuries, time is of the essence.
You must rinse the eye with clean water for at least 15 to 20 minutes without stopping.
When rinsing, position the head so the water flows from the inner corner of the eye toward
the outer corner.
This prevents the chemicals from washing across the bridge of the nose and into the unaffected
eye.
If the person is wearing contact lenses and can remove them easily, they should do so
while you continue the flushing process.
Before a physical hit to the eye, apply a cold pack to the area to help reduce pain
and swelling.
Call 911 immediately if they are experiencing severe pain, have any changes in their vision,
or if a chemical or object won't come out.